<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fern.18580814">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Blackwell's Island</title>
                <title type="sub">a machine-readable transcription</title>              
                <editor xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lf">Lisa Fruehling</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jordan Harper</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Fanny Fern in The New York Ledger, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:id="column">
                    <analytic>
                        <author xml:id="ff">Fanny Fern</author>
                        <title level="a">Blackwell's Island</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title xml:id="paper" level="j">The New York Ledger</title>
                        <editor xml:id="rb">Robert Bonner</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <date xml:id="issue_date" when="1858-08-14">14 August 1858</date>                    
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="pp">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="column">3</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                    <series>
                        <title level="s">Fresh Fern Leaves</title>
                    </series>
                </biblStruct>
                
                <biblStruct xml:id="issue">               
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j" sameAs="#paper"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <date sameAs="#issue_date"/>                  
                        </imprint>              
                    </monogr>                   
                </biblStruct>                        
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This electronic text is a semi-diplomatic transcription of the source text. Hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings, and errors present in the source text have been retained. The transcription does not attempt to capture all aspects of the original formatting or layout.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2024-11-11" who="#jh">proofed</change>
            <change when="2024-08-06" who="#lf">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <facsimile corresp="#issue">
        <surface xml:id="pp1">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.01.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp2">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.02.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp3">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.03.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp4" type="containsColumn">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.04.jpg"/> 
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp5">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.05.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp6">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.06.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp7">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.07.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp8">
            <graphic url="fern18580814.08.jpg"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
          
            <div type="column">
                <head type="column">FRESH FERN LEAVES.</head>
                
                <epigraph>
                    <p>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1855, by ROBERT BONNER, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the Southern District of New York.</p>
                </epigraph>
                
                
                    <head type="main">BLACKWELL'S ISLAND.</head>
                
                <head type="sub">NUMBER I.</head>
                
                <p>Prior to visiting Blackwell's Island last week, my ideas of that place were very forlorn and small-pox-y. It makes very little difference, to be sure, to a man, or a woman, shut up in a cell eight feet by four, how lovely are the out-door surroundings; how blue the river that plashes against the garden wall below, flecked with white sails, and alive with gay pleasure-seekers whose merry laugh has no monotone of sadness, that the convict wears the badge of degradation; and yet after all, one involuntarily says to oneself so instinctively so we turn to the cheerful side, I am glad they are located on this lovely island. Do you shrug your shoulders, Sir Cynic, and number over the crimes they have committed? Are <hi rend="italic">your</hi> crimes against society less, that they are written down only in God's book of remembrance? Are <hi rend="italic">you</hi> less guilty that you have been politic enough to commit only those that a short-sighted, unequal, human law sanctions? Shall I pity these poor wrecks of humanity less, because they are so recklessly self-wrecked? because they turn away from my pity? Before I come to this, I must know, as their Maker knows, what evil influences have encircled their cradles. How many times when their stomachs have been empty, some full-fed, whining disciple, has presented them with a Bible or a Tract, saying, Be ye warmed and filled. I must know how often when their feet have tried to climb the narrow, up-hill path of right, the eyes that have watched, have watched only for their halting; never noting, as God notes, the steps that did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> slip&#8212;never holding out the strong right hand of help when the devil with a full larder was tugging furiously at their skirts to pull them backward;&#8212;but only saying&#8212;"I told you so," when, laughing at your pharasaical stupidity, succeeded.</p>
                <p>I must go a great way back of those hard, defiant faces, where hate of their kind seems indelibly burnt in;&#8212;back&#8212;back&#8212;to the soft blue sky of infancy, overclouded before the little one had strength to contend with the flashing lightning and pealing thunder of misfortune and poverty which stunned and blinded his moral perceptions. I cannot see that mournful procession of men, filing off into those dark cells, none too dark, none too narrow, alas! to admit troops of devils, without wishing that some white-winged angel might enter too; and when their shining eye-balls peer at my retreating figure though the gratings, my heart shrieks out in its pain&#8212;oh! believe that there is pity here&#8212;only pity;&#8212;and I hate the bolts and bars, and I say this is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the way to make bad men good; or, at least if it be, these convicts should not, when discharged, be thrust out loose into the world with empty pockets, and a bad name, to earn a speedy "through-ticket" back again. I say, if this <hi rend="italic">be</hi> the way, let humanity not stop here, but take one noble step forward, and when she knocks off the convict's fetters, and lands him on the opposite shore, let her not turn her back and leave him there as if her duty were done; but let her <hi rend="italic">there</hi> erect a noble institution where he can find a <hi rend="italic">kind</hi> welcome and <hi rend="italic">instant</hi> employment; before temptation joining hands with his necessities, plunge him again headlong into the gulf of sin.</p>
                <p>And here seems to me to be the loose screw in all these institutions; admirably managed as many of them are, according to the prevalent ideas on the subject. You may tell me that I am a woman, and know nothing about it; and I tell you that I <hi rend="italic">want</hi> to know. I tell you, that I don't believe the way to restore a man's lost self respect, is to degrade him before his fellow-creatures; to brand him, and chain him, and poke him up to show his points, like a hyena in a menagerie. No wonder that he growls at you, and grows vicious; no wonder that he eats the food you thrust between the bars of his cage with gnashing teeth, and a vow to take it out of the world somehow, when he gets out; no wonder he thinks the Bible you place in his cell a humbug, and God a myth. I would have you startle up his self-respect by placing him in a position to show that you trusted him; I would have you give him something to hold in charge, for which he is in honor responsible ; appeal to his <hi rend="italic">better</hi> feelings, or if they smolder almost to extinction, fan them into a flame for him out of that remnant of God's image which the vilest can never wholly destroy. <hi rend="italic">Anything but shutting a man up with hell in his heart to make him good.</hi> The devils may well chuckle at it. And above all&#8212;tear down that taunting inscription over the prison-hall door at Blackwell's Island&#8212;"The way of transgressors is hard"&#8212;and place instead of it, "Neither do I condemn thee; go and sin no more."</p>
                    <byline>FANNY FERN.</byline>                
               
            </div>
            
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
