<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fern.18580612">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Hear! Hear!</title>
                <title type="sub">a machine-readable transcription</title>              
                <editor xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="np">Noelle Pinneo</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Fanny Fern in The New York Ledger, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:id="column">
                    <analytic>
                        <author xml:id="ff">Fanny Fern</author>
                        <title level="a">Hear! Hear!</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title xml:id="paper" level="j">The New-York Ledger</title>
                        <editor xml:id="rb">Robert Bonner</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <date xml:id="issue_date" when="1858-06-12">12 June 1858</date>                    
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="pp">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="column">3</biblScope> 
                    </monogr>
                    <series>
                        <title level="s">Fresh Fern Leaves</title>
                    </series>
                </biblStruct>
                
                <biblStruct xml:id="issue">               
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j" sameAs="#paper"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <date sameAs="#issue_date"/>                  
                        </imprint>              
                    </monogr>                   
                </biblStruct>                        
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This electronic text is a semi-diplomatic transcription of the source text. Hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings, and errors present in the source text have been retained. The transcription does not attempt to capture all aspects of the original formatting or layout.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2024-07-11" who="#np">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <facsimile corresp="#issue">
        <surface xml:id="pp1">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.01.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp2">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.02.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp3">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.03.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp4" type="containsColumn">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.04.jpg"/> 
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp5">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.05.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp6">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.06.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp7">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.07.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp8">
            <graphic url="fern18580612.08.jpg"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
          
            <div type="column">
                <head type="column">FRESH FERN LEAVES.</head>
                
                <epigraph>
                    <p>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1855, by ROBERT BONNER, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the Southern District of New York.</p>
                </epigraph>
                
                
                    <head type="main">HEAR! HEAR!</head>
                
                
                
                <p>Mr. Chairman, I rise to say, that there are no faults of sex; that there exist only faults of individuals. Prove it? Do not men say that "woman never proves anything, she only asserts?" Very well. I "<hi rend="italic">assert,</hi>" then, that men are just as fond of gossiping as women; one talks about the laces and shawls of her neighbor Mrs. Smith, how many times she has been married, and to whom; the other gets up scandal quite as virulent concerning political opponents, or business rivals. Women are no fonder of dress than men, only that men have the grace to do their prinking in the house; as everybody who has ever had the eye-range of hotel-windows, and knows what a work of time it is for them to locate a breast-pin, or set of studs, or to tie a cravat, or to wriggle into a new coat, can testify. Women are no vainer than men; the ugliest man alive always believes himself capable of attracting the prettiest woman. A walk in Broadway with one's eyes open will convince any skeptic of this. Women are no fonder of coquetting than men, only that the latter hide it under a thousand dignified humbugging names. Men are no more tolerant of a rival than women. The flattered beauty, with a sweet smile, presents her rival with a pomade, which, she assures her, will add lustre to her beautiful ringlets; but which, in fact, causes them all to drop off. Artists, when a new debutant makes a successful hit with a picture, do not refuse it a place in their public exhibition; but they take care to hang it in so bad a light, or to surround it with such unharmonious tints, that it shall be completely neutralized.</p>
                <p>Lady friends, it is said, when vexed with each other, betray one another's secrets; how is it with politicians when they turn their coats? Pshaw! it is six of one and half-a-dozen of the other; men are exactly like women about all these things, only a litle more so! For hundreds of years they have been peppering our sex, and we have been fools enough to bear it, with such proverbs as this&#8212;"when a woman will, she will, and when she won't, she won't, and there's an end of it;" as if we all did not know, though it has been as much as our necks were worth to say it, that one might as well try to pry up the Alps with a cambric needle, as to move a man's will when he plants his lordly foot down. Hitherto women, silently accepting this fact, have been content, where they could not contend, to <hi rend="italic">Delilah</hi> them out of it; but the day has gone by for such baby play. Women have the floor now, and the pen, too, Mr. Public; and you may take your seat. Wriggle in it you may; turn aside the great earnest questions of the day about woman's rights, in the flippant school-boy tone of the "New York Times," if you will; these questions, in which every husband, father and brother, who <hi rend="italic">truly</hi> respects our sex, should take a manly interest;&#8212;remember, they have yet to be met and settled. "Free Love" may bring discredit on them, by intruding its nauseous doctrine in their midst, and with a bland smile and winning speech, hold out freedom to woman with one hand, while with the other he is riveting, and <hi rend="italic">knows that he is riveting for his own selfish, sensual pleasure,</hi> her chains&#8212;tenfold tighter with the other. These tares must needs grow up with the wheat; still is the wheat there, silently ripening unto a harvest that we may never see, but which we may be well content to sow for other reapers.</p>
                    
                                   
                    <byline>FANNY FERN.</byline>                
               
            </div>
            
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
