<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fern.18581106">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">A Breakfast Reverie on Ledger Day.</title>
                <title type="sub">a machine-readable transcription</title>              
                <editor xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="np">Noelle Pinneo</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Fanny Fern in The New York Ledger, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:id="column">
                    <analytic>
                        <author xml:id="ff">Fanny Fern</author>
                        <title level="a">A Breakfast Reverie on Ledger Day.</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title xml:id="paper" level="j">The New-York Ledger</title>
                        <editor xml:id="rb">Robert Bonner</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <date xml:id="issue_date" when="1858-11-06">6 November 1858</date>                    
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="pp">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="column">3</biblScope> 
                    </monogr>
                    <series>
                        <title level="s">Fresh Fern Leaves</title>
                    </series>
                </biblStruct>
                
                <biblStruct xml:id="issue">               
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j" sameAs="#paper"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <date sameAs="#issue_date"/>                  
                        </imprint>              
                    </monogr>                   
                </biblStruct>                        
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This electronic text is a semi-diplomatic transcription of the source text. Hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings, and errors present in the source text have been retained. The transcription does not attempt to capture all aspects of the original formatting or layout.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2024-09-26" who="#np">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <facsimile corresp="#issue">
        <surface xml:id="pp1">
            <graphic url="fern18591106.01.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp2">
            <graphic url="fern18581106.02.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp3">
            <graphic url="fern18581106.03.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp4" type="containsColumn">
            <graphic url="fern18581106.04.jpg"/> 
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp5">
            <graphic url="fern18581106.05.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp6">
            <graphic url="fern18581106.06.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp7">
            <graphic url="fern18581106.07.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp8">
            <graphic url="fern18581106.08.jpg"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
          
            <div type="column">
                <head type="column">FRESH FERN LEAVES.</head>
                
                <epigraph>
                    <p>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1855, by ROBERT BONNER, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the Southern District of New York.</p>
                </epigraph>
                
                
                    <head type="main">A BREAKFAST REVERIE ON LEDGER DAY.</head>
                
                
                <p>What <hi rend="italic">did</hi> Adam and Eve do without newspapers? That's what I want to know. Nobody killed or married, no steamboat explosions, no railroad accidents. The beasts and beastesses all tame and well behaved; breakfast cooked to their taste, hanging ready on vine and bush; no clothes to mend; nothing to do but to make love all day long&#8212;not even the consolation of a cigar for Adam, or a bit of scandal for his rib. The serpent must have been a blessing; no wonder Eve dallied with him. "Satan finds some mischief still for idle hands to do," and heads, too. A newspaper would have saved her. In the first place, there would have been the excitement arising from her aggravating husband having the first reading of it, smoking all the while, so that she was obliged to pass it through quarantine before she could read all about "the frightful <hi rend="italic">lass</hi> of life," as the pathetic newsboys have it. I wonder would she have considered it swerving from her conjugal allegiance not to agree with Adam in politics, or on the great stirring questions of the day, and if she would have waxed warm in the discussions of them, and pulled his whiskers. I wonder if he <hi rend="italic">had</hi> whiskers. I thought of it the other Sunday "in meetin'," when the minister was reading about him. Of course I ought not, but I did; and I thought, too, how nice it must have been to be loved by the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> man, before his heart was riddled through and through like a target, as men's hearts are now-a-days, before they are twenty. I am afraid, though. Adam grew tame and stupid, else Eve never would have flirted with the serpent; not that I consider that an excuse&#8212;I wouldn't have you think so. Oh, no. In fact, I don't know why I made that remark. I suppose it must have been a natural one, though, else it would not have suggested itself; not that I approve of everything natural, either&#8212;not at all&#8212;and I wish you would not keep catching me up so on everything I say, as if I need weigh every word before I put it down. If there is anything I hate, it is writing that way; I won't do it for anybody except Mr. Bonner, who has too much good sense to ask it&#8212;who gives me a wide pasture to prance in, because he is sure that I will not jump the fence, though the conservatives sometimes needlessly hold their breath for fear I will.</p>
                <p>Well, it is a long jump from Adam and Eve to Mr. Bonner, and yet I can't help wishing they had been acquainted. I can't help thinking that if Adam had subscribed, like other good husbands, for the <!-- small caps? -->NEW YORK LEDGER, Eve never would have got into trouble. I'm convinced of it, and have long since ceased upbraiding her for that very reason. It was not her fault that Sylvanus Cobb, Jr., and Emerson Bennett were not born. The panthers and lions about her were all well enough, but they didn't show fight; there were no perilous adventures, no hair-breadth escapes, no storms, no "row" any how; she tired of dew and humming birds, just as I should. Now think what a blessing Bennett and Cobb would have been; think of the agonizing delight of leaving a heroine hanging by the eyelids, not to be extricated from her perilous position till the following Thursday, when the next <!-- small caps? --> LEDGER should be "out," for they know too much to leave their readers easy in their minds a whole week. Ah, you may sniff at them, you superfine fellows, who find it difficult to keep yourselves in cigars; but if they were not wanted they would not be run after, I can tell you that.</p>
                <p>I should like to compute the lips which say every Thursday, "Ah, 'tis <!-- small caps? --> LEDGER day, is it not?" I never see that printing press flying round like mad in Fulton street, throwing the sheets to the four winds, that I don't feel like giving three cheers for Robert Bonner whose heart is as big as his subscription list, and that's saying considerable, and who deserves, a hundred times told, every mill that his industry and energy have earned; and now, when he reads this, he may blush if he likes&#8212;I shan't.</p>
                    
                                   
                    <byline>FANNY FERN.</byline>                
               
            </div>
            
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
