<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fern.18581120.01">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">A Life Sketch</title>
                <title type="sub">a machine-readable transcription</title>              
                <editor xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="np">Noelle Pinneo</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Fanny Fern in The New York Ledger, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:id="column">
                    <analytic>
                        <author xml:id="ff">Fanny Fern</author>
                        <title level="a">A Life Sketch</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title xml:id="paper" level="j">The New-York Ledger</title>
                        <editor xml:id="rb">Robert Bonner</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <date xml:id="issue_date" when="1858-11-20">20 November 1858</date>                    
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="pp">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="column">3</biblScope> 
                    </monogr>
                    <series>
                        <title level="s">Fresh Fern Leaves</title>
                    </series>
                </biblStruct>
                
                <biblStruct xml:id="issue">               
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j" sameAs="#paper"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <date sameAs="#issue_date"/>                  
                        </imprint>              
                    </monogr>                   
                </biblStruct>                        
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This electronic text is a semi-diplomatic transcription of the source text. Hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings, and errors present in the source text have been retained. The transcription does not attempt to capture all aspects of the original formatting or layout.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2024-10-08" who="#np">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <facsimile corresp="#issue">
        <surface xml:id="pp1">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.01.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp2">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.02.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp3">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.03.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp4" type="containsColumn">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.04.jpg"/> 
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp5">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.05.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp6">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.06.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp7">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.07.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp8">
            <graphic url="fern18581120.01.08.jpg"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
          
            <div type="column">
                <head type="column">FRESH FERN LEAVES.</head>
                
                <epigraph>
                    <p>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1855, by ROBERT BONNER, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the Southern District of New York.</p>
                </epigraph>
                
                
                    <head type="main">A LIFE SKETCH.</head>
                
                
                
                    <p>A small, dark, cheerless room, an unshapely bed, upon which lay an unshapely remnant of humanity, whose faded eyes had wandered up and down those barren chamber walls, till every crack and crevice was as familiarly mapped out to the closed, as to the open eye. Everything dark and dingy, colorless and dreary; the propped up, worm-eaten table, and three-legged chair, and fireless hearth, and broken-paned window with its stuffing of rags; the wailing wind that whistled through them,&#8212;passing away! passing away! Mournful memories, the slow, sad procession of lost hopes trailing their tarnished, world begrimed brightness through the accumulated dust of years, palsying the tongue, filming over the eyes that still, while life lingers, roam with unspeakable and restless longings for something to rest upon beside darkness, gloom and decay.</p>
                    <p>Now and then a neighbor, poor and care-worn as herself, looked in upon the bed-ridden old woman. Short time they had, God knows, in the hurrying scramble for daily bread, to think or care for aught else; none of them knew her history; none knew how little she whose limbs had once been so daintily decked ever dreamed to lie through those weary days, and weeks, and moments, so helpless, so friendless, prisoned in from the blue sky, the sweet flowers, the green earth, biding her time to be carried out by careless hands to lie beneath them.</p>
                    <p>'Twas weary waiting&#8212;'twas weary listening for some voice that had music in it, 'twas weary looking only upon faces trouble-seamed and care-worn as her own.</p>
                <p>The door opens gently, and the light streams in through the doorway full upon a young girl, fresh as if just from the hand of God, upon locks like vine tendrils upon the rosy cheek, and eyes of heavenly blue, upon the sweet mouth with its pitying smile&#8212;filling the dingy room with a brightness like one of God's own angels. The old woman raised herself upon her elbow and gazed upon the maiden, as one would gaze upon a flower in the desert,&#8212;upon a star in a rayless night,&#8212;upon the bright winged bird which lights for a brief moment upon the tempest-tost ship. Then&#8212;sinking back upon <choice><sic>ner</sic><corr>her</corr></choice> pillow with a murmur like the home sick <choice><sic>mariher</sic><corr>mariner</corr></choice> in his dreams, she sighs, ah, me! how beautiful is youth!</p>
                    
                                   
                    <byline>FANNY FERN.</byline>                
               
            </div>
            
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
